[Music]
so
hello good evening good day everybody
welcome to the latest episode of the ask
a budget show
i hope you're all doing very well
as you know today is a science and
technology episode so before we we begin
let's
see who all is with us
so i can see her stages canal priyanchi
[Music]
lord mountain
real
foreign and lots of other people uh good
evening good day all of you great to be
back amongst you again
and with that said let's get into the
questions
so as always i've picked a bunch of
questions and let us begin with question
number one
which is a very popular question right
now so this is by uh nikhil
nikhil says can you express your opinion
on the mysterious rocket crash on the
moon recently
no country is taking responsibility for
it
has it really happened or is it just a
fake news viraling around
yeah so this news has appeared in recent
days in in the past few days that
a couple of new craters have formed on
the moon
and uh
it appears like there's been some kind
of uh
recent crash on the moon
and they're saying it's a rocket crash
or some kind of spacecraft that has
crashed there
not a natural
impact like asteroids
and apparently no country has taken
responsibility for that so that's what
we hear let me see what the news looks
like moon moon
trash uh let me share my screen and see
what i'm searching for
yeah nasa
baffled by mystery rocket with unknown
origin
so you can see a couple of craters over
there and that's happened and apparently
nasa is baffled
and adds as always
so that's what they say apparently there
is some kind of crash
and we don't know what it is
so that's the news so what's my opinion
on this so uh
there are a couple of possibilities
first of all maybe uh nasa knows maybe
the americans know know who it is maybe
it's their own spacecraft or their own
space debris
maybe it's china maybe it's russia maybe
it's some other country
uh typically what happens is that all of
these spacecraft that are launched into
space are tracked
especially by the americans and i'm sure
by other countries as well
so i it is very unlikely that they don't
know
who it is that's responsible for this
crash in case it is uh
uh space debris or a spacecraft
so either they know and they're not
revealing it
or something is fishy
maybe it's aliens huh so there's always
that possibility that maybe there is
some alien involvement in this crash
so uh
to to be to be to to be to be serious i
don't think it is
the case that the americans don't know
what it is most likely they know who is
behind this and maybe they don't want to
reveal it for whatever
reason so yeah so that's where we are
it is still a mystery and i expect that
over time it will be revealed and
cleared up
okay swarup vedia says last year a motor
motor neuron diseased patient
became the first person to tweet a
message using only his brain
this was made possible by a microchip
that was implanted into the brain
the chip allows patients to carry out
computer tasks just using their minds
do you think this will be as common as
having a mobile in the near future when
the price of the chip at the surgery
will be affordable
i think eventually this could become
quite common
uh
initially it will be used for people who
are quadriplegics and people who are
paralyzed people who are who have the
so-called locked in syndrome which means
that they are fully conscious but they
are locked inside their body is
completely unresponsive and they are
unable to control the body for whatever
reason using their mind
so the body appears like it's in the
vegetative state but the person inside
is fully conscious and aware of what's
happening
and you can
figure this out using brain scans and
all that you know when you ask a
question the brain responds immediately
to that which shows a
response to external stimulus which
means the person is conscious to some
extent and when you implant these trips
then you can actually possibly
communicate with the person
so uh this technology is currently a
work in progress
but like you say like you said here uh
this has happened uh
i even heard that some that a person
with a
brain implant a chip implanted in the
brain was able to surf the internet
and order order coke or a pizza or
something like that you know or or
or ask the computer to place
their favorite music so that sort of
thing is currently uh definitely
possible with the technology that we
have today
it will eventually become more common
it will first be used for patients who
suffer from these problems but
eventually it will be
implanted in fully functional
human beings
to enhance their abilities so this is
called transhumanism and that's what
elon musk is doing with his uh
neural link project that company which
aims to implant microchips in the brains
of perfectly
healthy and normal human beings and that
will give them uh
certain capabilities that we typically
don't have right so maybe you'll be able
to surf the internet right away without
needing your fingers to type or whatever
you'll be able to directly
issue commands to the to your wi-fi or
whatever using your brain using your
mind using your thoughts
and you may be able to uh eventually
instead of using screens you may be able
to visualize data and images right in
your brain using this technology so that
could happen
so i think initially there's going to be
some uh
skepticism about this kind of technology
because people will be wondering whether
this sort of implant could cause any
brain damage
or not
or whether it's going to be used to
control your mind you know there's going
to be all kinds of
fears
and definitely initially there will be
hesitancy and resistance but as more and
more people over time
adopt this technology it will become
more and more common and then eventually
there will be a tip point when everybody
wants it
but of course like i've said before in
the past there are
potential problems
and uh
so that's something that
people need to keep in mind
so yeah
i think eventually it will become quite
common just like having mobiles i mean
it took a it took a long time for
mobiles to
become ubiquitous
the technology was first introduced in
the 1990s if i'm not mistaken by
vodafone in england
and it took at least a decade before it
became like reasonably prevalent
and it's on the only the 21st century
that it totally took off
uh in other countries especially in
india etc so it takes time but i think
eventually
uh this could become quite common
okay lakshay says
is human cloning possible if yes then
why are scientists not allowed to do the
do to work towards it
except in cases when they are doing
something unethical we might enhance
human capability and enhance this
eliminate diseases through it
so
what is cloning cloning is
so cloning is certainly possible
uh the first organism
or or large scale organism to be cloned
was dolly the sheep which is like i
think in the 1990s
and many other species and other animals
have been cloned in
subsequent
years
i think the technology is quite advanced
and i'm sure it is certainly possible to
clone human beings as well
so what is cloning cloning is you take a
person's dna
and you implant it into a new fertilized
egg or whatever and that creates a
complete
new human being with the exact same dna
so that is what cloning is
whether it's a human being or a
butterfly or whatever other species but
that is the principle behind
cloning
i am sure it is certainly possible to
clone human beings by now
i think such experiments may even have
been undertaken in countries like china
they have been cloning other animals
like monkeys etc yeah
they have been doing that
uh but that certainly does raise ethical
questions
is it ethical to do this is it ethical
to create designer human beings
for whatever
purpose that you have for whatever
whatever agenda you're trying to fulfill
so that's always a question
so the
question
is always about ethics when it comes to
experimentation on human beings any kind
of experimentation
actually it should it should extend to
other species also because i mean
it could cause
pain and suffering you know
experimentation could cause pain
suffering etc on to other species
to other animals and that's a something
that happens the animal experimentation
that that's a routine practice in
in well industries like uh cosmetics and
all that
so human cloning i believe is definitely
100 percent possible
uh what would be the uh
need
to clone somebody
why would you want to clone someone
so that's the question
it is certainly possible to do it but
why would you want to do it
i mean
it would have some agenda or some
purpose behind it and is it ethical to
create new human beings to serve some
agenda or to fulfill some purpose
that is a big question and i would say
it's it's not ethical to to create human
beings for for a certain purpose human
being should have a purpose that is
their own
they should not be owned by somebody
they should not be created by somebody
and they should not be designed by
somebody and and that person will
decide what sort of genetics this new
human will have should not work like
that
so that's the ethical
uh concern that's always there and
that's why cloning
human experimentation is is illegal in
most
most countries right
so yeah that's the reason and when you
speak about enhancing various
capabilities and eliminate eliminating
diseases
that's about gene editing that's about
those technologies that emerge out of
something like crispr
so there is gene editing
there is creating genetically modified
organisms that's been done in
agriculture and other things
and once again it does raise ethical
questions
because you can today you do have the
ability to edit
the human genome using crispr but do we
know what's going to be the long-term
effect of that
on that individual and in future
generations we don't quite know
we don't understand the genome fully we
understand about four percent of the
genome and that too
not very well
about 95 or 96 of the genome is
completely
dark they call it the dark matter of the
dna
and if you understand so little of the
human genome is it
wise to tinker with it
without understanding how the whatever
you're doing is going to affect the
other part of part of the genome
so you know this can be a slippery slope
it can cause dangerous unintended
unforeseen effects
and that's why one has to be very
careful while doing this and for this
reason for for all of these reasons
uh
human experimentation and cloning and
genetic
whatever all of that is currently banned
in most countries
i expect in some places it may some some
experiments may be ongoing
secretly
but yeah there's no evidence of that so
that's where we are
okay erickson says there are claims by
people who worked in area 51 like bob
lazar that the u.s has access to
extraterrestrial technology he mentions
a gravity generation based spacecraft
and are trying to figure it out is it
possible that the us government has
technology that's vastly more advanced
than what we use in terms of energy
generation
space travel and military technology if
yes which other governments can have
access to such technology let me take
the second question first
is it possible that the us government
has access to technology that we don't
quite know about yes of course
they have been developing all kinds of
technologies
and
all of this new technology that's being
developed for military purposes it's
completely classified it's top secret
it's not revealed to the public for
decades
so there are certain aircraft
that where whose existence was revealed
uh
for instance the space the stealth
aircraft its existence was was revealed
the the
spirit bomber b1 i think it is a b2
whatever whichever one it is
its existence was revealed
at the time around the time of the first
gulf war 91 is it 1991
but that aircraft had been around
and it had been in use for at least a
decade before that
similarly the sr-71 blackbird
that's another aircraft that has been
retired now
that too
was kept under wraps for a very long
time
so typically these technologies which
are the at the cutting edge of what's
possible
these are kept under wraps for decades
there are i can guarantee this there are
technologies
in use right now in the u.s military
that whose existence will not be
revealed for the next two three four
decades it's quite possible
yeah and it's not just the u.s other
countries as well
will be working on such technologies
and they obviously will want to keep it
under wraps because they don't want
other nations to become aware of what
their military capabilities are
and that's why deception and stealth is
is paramount
in
military matters in geopolitics and all
that
so yeah it is certainly possible that
the us government has
very advanced technology that we are not
aware of and which is which will not be
revealed for decades to come and
stability for russia for china for india
as well possibly it's quite possible
so one can only speculate about this
because we don't have information this
information is not going to be made
available in the public domain
now about the first question about area
51 bob laser and
extraterrestrial technology i am
extraordinarily skeptical about this
i i am quite certain
that we are not the only uh planet on
which life exists
i'm certain that there are other planets
other other star systems other galaxies
etc
where life
intelligent life exists i i would i
imagine i
i am convinced
that intelligent life could be quite
common in our universe it's just that we
haven't found it maybe we are too
primitive to be able to
detect
evidence of intelligent life okay
whatever it is that is a different story
so i am convinced i am very
very sure
that intelligent life does exist
in other places as well in other other
star systems
but the likelihood
of such
intelligent life having visited the
earth is very remote
it's very unlikely it's not zero the
probability is not zero but it's
close to zero
now
let's assume for a second that aliens
did visit the earth
and they have established contact with
human beings
why is it that they would only contact
the united states
why
for what reason
and why are ufos only visible in in the
us night sky or de sky
why are there no
uh
reports of ufos in india
or sri lanka
yeah why why not why not in
denmark why not in the philippines
why not in kenya why is it always the
united states where you get these ufo
sightings
is it is there something really special
about the people who live in the u.s
so that's one thing that doesn't make
any sense if aliens
have
established contact with humans and they
do visit the the earth then why don't
other nations witness ufos right and why
have they if they have provided their
technology to uh to humans why is it
only to the us government
so that's that sounds like a hollywood
kind of story you know
so that's why i'm very skeptical about
this
uh it's possible that aliens may
may be around
yeah but then if it is so then we should
all be able to see that or at least
there should be reports reliable refer
reports in other countries as well
so because of all these reasons i am
very skeptical about this area 51 story
this bob laser story i'm sure i mean
i i haven't seen his interviews and i
have not read his whatever he may have
written so i i can't really comment
about that about his claims whatever
they may be
but i am very skeptical about this
i believe that
i am
reasonably certain that aliens i mean
intelligent aliens exist in other other
planets other stores star systems and so
on but i am very skeptical about these
claims that they have visited us and
they are in they are working hand in
glove with the us government they have
provided
their alien technology only to the
americans and nobody to nobody else
because americans are somehow special
and exceptional what nonsense
aliens don't care about any of that so
that's how it is and that's why i am
skeptical about this matter
akash says are the ideas of exploring
black holes traveling at the speed of
light time machines and warp drive and
other such concepts
valueless or do they have any real
utility even if as a thought experiment
usually the non-professionals seem
really interested in these
rather than real scientists
all of these uh concepts and ideas are
real ideas
they make sense from the perspective of
physics
uh traveling at the speed of light is
not possible we know that i mean the
equations tell us
and until we have new equations that
prove the other one the existing ones
wrong we have to under we have to agree
that the
best equations the best theories that we
have are the valid theories as of today
in the future we will have better
theories and maybe in the future in the
22nd century perhaps we'll have a theory
which says that yeah you can travel at
the speed of light but as of today the
best theory that we have
is general relativity which says it's
impossible to travel at the speed of
light so
these ideas what they do
is that
they
take us forward
what if we could travel at the speed of
light so that makes us explore physics
in greater depth black holes were a
fantasy for a very long time until well
we
were able to detect certain
astrophysical objects that look very
much like black holes we still don't
have 100 confirmation that these are
black holes with singularities within
and all that but they look very much
like black holes
uh time machines well even time travel
is theoretically possible there are
certain uh solutions of the einstein
equations field equations which would uh
actually allow you go to go back in time
there are multiple scenarios in which
this would be possible this could be
possible which is something i went into
in the in the previous
uh science episode
what drives drives again could be
possible
once again there are certain solutions
of the einstein field equations that are
could make
uh traveling within
a bubble of space time which itself is
traveling faster than the speed of light
even that could be
possible yeah so many of these things
are actually theoretically within the
realms of possibility
as of course as of today we don't have
the technology we don't have anything
remotely close to the technology that we
would need to make them possible but yes
it is something that
does drive
physics forward
and
thought experiments are at the core of
theoretical physics
right
so it these are very important these are
important uh questions important
concepts important ideas important
avenues to explore
i agree that non-professionals seem
more interested in this than real
scientists
when you're a scientist you have to uh
exhibit a certain
uh
amount of skepticism
and you you have to show that you have
your feet firmly on the ground and
you're not going off on wild goose
changes chases
and very often when you are a
professional physicist you are actually
trying to solve smaller problems
rather than solve the biggest problems
of the them all
because it is the smaller problems that
eventually lead you towards the bigger
problems so it appears
especially to outsiders especially to
our non-professionals
like
the professional scientists physicists
are not so interested in these matters
which is not quite the case
we are all interested in this but uh
we we tend to keep the uh
the
apparent visual level of excitement a
little bit toned it down that's what it
is
and of course we haven't made any
massive breakthroughs in these matters
so as of today we still don't have a
viable technology which will allow us to
create a warp drive or a time machine or
to allow us to go back in time
and certainly not traveling at the speed
of light but of course we have things
that come close
for instance we have the breakthrough
star shot uh project that in the next 10
to 20 years could launch
a bunch of spacecraft
micro spacecraft towards our nearest
star at 20 or 30 the speed of light
which is a massive massive uh
quantum leap in terms of capabilities
you know we would need certain
technologies to be developed uh
such as
phased lasers and all that you know but
it's certainly
within the realms of possibility in the
near term
so i think from my perspective at least
all of these ideas are fascinating they
are very exciting and there is something
that
should
and is being pursued and
the actual utility of these ideas is
that it draws in young minds
right
that's what really evokes curiosity and
fascination
and in excitement as a youngster as a 12
year old as a 15 year old you want to be
fascinated by something and that's what
makes you want to be a scientist right
and it is these ideas like black holes
and time
machines and warp drives and traveling
close to the speed of light exploring
other star systems
maybe creating a gravitational wave
spectroscope or whatever you know
that's what fascinates you and that's
what
makes you want to enter the field and
make a genuine contribution big
contribution i want to solve the big
problems right
so that's great
so i think all of these things have
genuine real
utility of course
even if we solve certain of some of
these problems the actual uh
real world utility could come much later
for instance when einstein came up with
the theory of relativity uh general
relativity 1915 it took a hundred years
for us to actually discover
uh gravitational waves and yet and even
today we don't have any technology that
uses
gravitational waves uh the only
technology that uses a general
relativity as far as i can
as far as i can remember is gps
so in for for gps to work you need
uh to incorporate the effects of general
relativity otherwise it doesn't work it
won't be accurate so it takes time
theoretical physics is at the cutting
edge of the bleeding edge of
research in physics
and it's typically decades or even
centuries ahead of what
the experimentalists
are at
so the
applications take a long time to become
apparent but it's without the
work that's that's done by theoretical
physicists none of the applications are
possible so that's how it is so it has
its utility
swapnan says can you differentiate
between the two theories for the origin
of life primordial soup and deep sea
vents
because they both seem similar
so uh
the primordial super theory is that in
the very early uh days of the earth
when you had the
newly formed earth which was formed out
of the
chaos of the infant of the infancy of
the solar system
the the proto
solar disk and all that so in the very
early earth
you had what is called the primal soup
which is all these
hot very hot swirling gases
uh you had
carbon dioxide you had a whole mixture
of gases
uh you would have methane
ammonia
water vapor and many other things the
temperatures were very high there was a
lot of lightning and all that and it is
out of this primordial soup that life
emerged somehow
right so that is the
that's the uh
experiment we spoke about
last week
i don't recall the name of the
experiment
yuri teller or something like that so
that was an experiment that sought to
recreate the conditions of the very
early earth
in a test tube kind of apparatus you
know in a lab apparatus and they were
able to
show
that if you create the same kind of
environment
inside the apparatus
you can uh
very very quickly you find the emergence
of amino acids and all that
so that is the primordial soup theory
that it is out of such conditions in the
very early earths
that
life emerged
so that's one theory the other theory
like you mentioned is deep sea vents so
what are deep sea vents
so
we know that the earth has a crust
below the crust there is the mantle
below that there is the magma layer the
magma layer is the molten rock
and below
the magma layer at the core of the earth
you have this very solid
uh
core which is mostly metallic
right nickel iron all that so that's the
that's the
cross section of the earth let's let's
take a look at what it looks like
one second let me
share my screen so that you get an idea
of what i'm talking about
the earth structure
if it ever loads
okay
so what you have is the crust the upper
crust the lower crust the outer core in
the core
and of course there is the magma layer
the mantle inner core all that so this
is what the cross section of the earth
looks like
now we have what's known as plate
tectonics
uh which says the
which is a phenomenon in which uh the
crust of the earth moves because of the
convection
of the magma layer below
and from time to time there are
fractures and fissures
in the crust of the earth and the magma
comes out
and that's what causes volcanism and
things like that now there are lots of
underwater volcanoes under sea volcanoes
and uh you see the same kind of volcanic
activity under the ocean
these are called deep sea vents so let
me show you what deep sea vents look
like
right so if you go deep under the
surface
of the ocean on the on the
to the bottom of the ocean you have
these deep sea vents
which are essentially uh
manifestations of volcanic activity
and
so what happens in these deep sea vents
is that the temperatures are very very
high like typically boiling point of
water and you have all these gases
that come out of the surface
of the uh
of the ocean floor
so you have sulfur you have methane and
various other volcanic gases
so all of this creates a very rich
environment rich in chemicals very hot
and surprisingly you have all this life
that thrives over there and this is the
kind of life that doesn't need sunlight
because it gets energy from the
heated
water and all the chemicals
so you have these uh tube worms etc that
live in these that thrive in these deep
sea winds so it's a very specialized
kind of life that lives there under the
very high pressure of the of the ocean
so that is another theory like you say
of the origin of life that maybe life
originated in deep sea events and then
moved upwards and spread to other parts
of the of the planet so these are the
two
uh theories that you're speaking about
and it's it's possible both are
both are viable theories good theories
that could possibly explain the
uh a biogenesis the origin of life out
of chemicals
with these with these energy sources etc
available so that's what the two
theories are
and they are not quite similar of course
the the
they are similar in some ways and
dissimilar in some ways so that's what
these two theories are
and we still don't know how life emerged
we still don't have the exact uh the
exact answer the exit idea
and we off definitely don't know where
dna came from
how does a molecule as complex as dna
emerge because dna is what is at the
foundation of all life on our planet
whether it is we human beings whether it
is dogs cats wolves elephants leopards
butterflies insects
fish
microorganisms viruses bacteria whatever
it is
every single living being every single
living cell
has dna in it of course in the human
body
red blood cells don't have dna
but apart from that right so
so yeah so we don't have the answers as
of today
karon says our ancestors memory is
locked in our dna question mark
so you're asking whether our ancestors
memories are locked in our dna
can we inherit our ancestors memories by
gene memory unlocking technique
various startups are working on this
what will happen if it is really
possible
is it possible that some of our
ancestors memories could be locked up in
our dna it's possible possibly yeah
it's not impossible
but we don't quite know what it is
what we do know is that we understand
only about four or five percent of our
genome
about 95 percent of it is completely
unknown to us we don't know what it does
it doesn't seem to code for any proteins
and some people have called it junk dna
but you know nature is parsimonious
nature doesn't
indulge in wastage
why would it pass on so much junk from
generation to generation over hundreds
of thousands of years doesn't make any
sense
that
dna needs to have some purpose it has to
have some purpose
so we don't know what it is
does it mean there are there are
memories encoded in that we don't know
we don't quite remember what our
ancestors
experienced right
so uh so i personally don't know of
course we do find articles written about
this that there could be certain
memories
locked up encoded in our dna memories of
our ancestors experiences or whatever
and maybe one could unlock that using
certain techniques so yes there is a
research that's being done in this field
but as of today
nobody has any definitive evidence
that this is indeed the case
so nobody has been able to say unlock a
certain portion of a certain person's
genome and say that you know these are
the memories that were stored in here no
that's not happened yet
but people are researching this it's
being taken seriously and maybe there is
something to it so this is a work in
progress it's a very interesting and
interesting feed for sure um interesting
uh question and idea
and
whether we find memories or not
we don't know
but it will certainly uh take us forward
in understanding
what the dna is what our genome is like
95 is unknown we don't know what it does
we don't know what it codes for we don't
know what its purpose is
hopefully this sort of research will
unlock some of that at least at least
we'll be able to shed some
fresh light some new light on on our
genome
so that's where we are that's what's
happening right now
very interesting field
biology dna genetics all that so yeah
let's see how it goes
pierce says how omnipotent is
gravitation do we apply do we both apply
gravitational force
even when we are far apart which is
almost negligible okay i'm able to
understand the first part of the
question how omnipotent is gravitation
gravitation is all omnipotent
so i am sitting here in my study in this
room yeah
i am right now
feeling the effects of the gravitation
of the planet of the earth which is
right straight down that's where the
force is coming from but i'm also
feeling
to some extent the gravitational effect
of the moon wherever it is i don't know
where it is right now but i'm feeling it
i'm also feeling the gravitational
effect of the sun
of the other planets
however little it is but it's there
and i'm also
and so are you we are all also feeling
the gravity of the other stars that are
out there in our galaxy we are feeling
the gravitational effect of the black
hole at the center of our galaxy
sagittarius a
and we are feeling the gravitational
effects of every other star planet
galaxy
dust particle etc that exists throughout
the universe
gravity is a long-range force it's it's
it's in its range is infinite
right
so yes we've gravitation is omnipotent
it's everywhere it's the weakest force
but it's the
uh
from the newtonian perspective it's a
one upon r4 so it never goes to zero
you always feel a certain component of
uh
of gravitation of every single particle
and
ma massive object that exists in the in
the universe right
so what we feel here is the resultant
of all of these different components and
all of the
gravitation that you feel from other all
the other objects that exist in the
universe
so yes that's that's what it is
okay the question is i recently read i
recently read an amanda american
scientist report which says that the
extreme atmospheric pressure of neptune
uranus
saturn etc can crystallize carbon atoms
and turn them into diamonds is it true
how can it happen
so carbon comes in in a variety of forms
let me show you what the forms are like
carbon
allotropes
let's see
so these are the various allotropes of
carbon let's take a look at this
so
diamond graphite whatever this is c60
buckminster fullerene
c540 c70 amorphous carbon
single walled carbon nanotubes
and these various shapes
right
so carbon exists in all of these
different forms which are called
allotropes
uh so how does diamond typically form
diamond typically forms when you when
you take a lump of carbon let's say a
lump of coal and you
exert an enormous amount of pressure on
it
and when that happens the carbon takes
the for
the form of diamond that's what happens
so diamond is just carbon it's another
form of coal you could say and it's
formed in the interior of the planet
where the pressures are very high
now if you have a lump of carbon that
exists that you throw let's say you take
a lump of coal a big lump of coal you
throw it
at jupiter
jupiter is an enormous planet we know
that
huge amount of mass
and it is a gaseous planet it doesn't
have a surface so you throw a lump of
carbon at this planet it's going to sink
it's going to go down
deeper and deeper into the planet and as
it goes deeper into the interior of the
planet it's going to be it's going to
uh
it's going to
experience
atmospheric pressure that keeps rising
as it goes as it goes deeper towards the
center
and eventually the atmospheric pressure
is going to be so high
that this lump of coal or carbon is
going to be squeezed and it's going to
turn into diamond
yeah
so that's typically something that would
happen
inside a massive planet like jupiter or
saturn possibly even uranus or neptune
which are also gas giants right
so it is
possible
that over time
we know carbon is
is quite common in the solar system many
of the asteroids
have a lot of carbon on them
you know that
so and we also know that asteroids go
keep on hitting planets like jupiter
saturn etc from time to time asteroids
comets etc right
so
the the solar system is a very is a very
old system
uh how old is it three and a half
billion years old four and a half i'm
not sure whatever like whatever it is it
is billions of years old and over these
billions billions of years a planet like
jupiter or saturn would have absorbed
impacts from uncountable numbers of
asteroids and comets
and the carbon
in these
objects would have sunk towards the
center of the planet jupiter
and it would have crystallized into into
diamond
so it is quite likely
that at the core
of these gaseous
planets the gas giants like jupiter
saturn uranus neptune etc
it is quite likely that at the core you
would have a massive amount of diamond
you may even have a fully diamond core
possibly possibly it's possible
so that's how it happens because of the
enormous atmospheric pressure that
squeezes
carbon
into its diamond allotrope
so it is
quite likely that there is an enormous
amount of diamond
near the core or at the core of jupiter
saturn uranus and neptune within our own
solar system quite likely
isn't that interesting
okay the next question is by neil mehta
in one of your previous videos you
mentioned about grigori perelman
and you called him a one in a billion
kind of mathematician but why is there
little to no information about him on
the internet not even a single interview
could you tell more about him and his
solution of the funkare conjecture
so the prank area conjecture i will not
go into what it is it's a very old
problem it was there it was uh
uh around for more than a century and
lots of mathematicians tried to solve it
and they all failed and eventually this
gentleman gregory perelman was able to
solve it
now why are there no interviews about
him and no information because he's a
very
shy reclusive private kind of person he
does not give interviews
that's the kind of person he is
there have been many personalities like
that for instance in cricket you had
this guy called curtly ambrose a west
indies fast bowler who would never give
interviews to anyone
nowadays of late he has changed and he's
become more social but for the longest
time it was like that
so many many people are like that
so grigori paranoman is a very very
private person very shy person reclusive
person he doesn't want fame he
he refused to accept the field medal
which is the greatest
honor a mathematician could have
it's even
higher
than the nobel prize
right
the nobel prize is given every year
in physics and various other fields
right
the fields metal is given out once in
four years only to people
under 40.
that's an enormous honor and it comes
with a price tag price tag of a million
dollars i think
and he refused that
so he doesn't want any fame or
recognition he says that the only
recognition i want is that the solution
that i gave is correct and that's that's
enough for me
that's the kind of person he is and of
course he was very hurt by the attempts
of certain mathematicians to steal his
proof uh let me show you what that is
uh one second so let us go back to
google
there is the thing all right
so there is this article very famous
article
in the new yorker magazine
which is called manifold destiny the
clash over the poincare conjecture
a legendary problem in the battle over
who solved it
and the one of the authors is sylvia
nasser who also is the author of this
very famous book called a beautiful mind
so this cartoon
the caption says is that
uh grigori pelan perelman on the right
says if the proof is correct then no
other recognition is needed
but
shin tung yao isn't so sure
so this chinese origin mathematician
ching
essentially attempted to steal the
credit from grigori paraman what
perelman did is that he solved the
problem
so so
this is the name of the article manifold
destiny i if you are interested i would
recommend you read it it's a very
interesting article
it came out in 2006.
so what happened is that this guy
peralman
he proved the puankari conjecture
and he wrote up a paper with detailing
the entire proof
and he did not submit it to a
peer-reviewed journal he simply placed
it
on a preprint archive
on the pre-print archive archive.org a
rxiv.org and it just said that and
eventually people realized that this guy
has solved the conjecture so this
chinese guy what's his name
what's his name
yao
he's he's also a very famous
mathematician i i believe he has also
been awarded the fields fields medal
so shin tang yao what he did is that he
picked up the proof
and he he wrote a new paper along with a
couple of students of his
or maybe they wrote the paper they were
the primary authors or whatever
in which they
expanded upon the proof
elaborated upon the proof and said that
this is the crowning achievement
and they kind of tried to
take credit for
giving the full proof of the bronchitic
conjecture that's the kind of thing that
happened
eventually an indian mathematician or
student
graduate student picked up the
similarities between the two papers and
he pointed out that the chinese guys had
essentially plagiarized pearlman's paper
and then there were retractions and they
said that we are not and they changed
the some of the terminology and they
said they
withdrew the term crowning achievement
and all that
and eventually they were essentially
shamed that's what happened
but it doesn't seem to have done the the
reputation of shinge tang yao too much
of harm
that's how it is
so because of this experience perelma
kind of withdrew into a shell and i
think he just quit mathematics he quit
doing mathematics after that
and i'm not sure what he's up to these
days but uh yeah he's not
he's clearly not active in mathematics
anymore
so that's how it is he's that's kind of
that kind of person a very shy reclusive
kind of person very private person and
he was deeply hurt by all of this
controversy and the attempts to steal
the credit from him and that's why he is
now withdrawn
from the field and
he doesn't give interviews
so i if you are interested i would
recommend you read that uh this this
article manifold destiny very
interesting piece of
mathematical history
swapnil says hypothetically speaking if
we raised the level of atmospheric
oxygen
in the environment would it be better or
worse for the human species during the
carboniferous period there used to be
giant insects as the atmospheric oxygen
content
used to be at 35 percent but humans were
not evolved
yet uh
it is extremely dangerous
to tinker with the uh
environment in any manner
right now the percentage of oxygen in
the atmosphere is about 20 21 i believe
yeah
if you raise it by 14 it could have
catastrophic
consequences for the environment
there was a time
when our planet had a very different
atmospheric composition there was almost
no oxygen
and we had life on the planet
then a certain species of bacteria
started proliferating in the oceans
of the world i believe these were called
cyanobacteria
and
they uh
so
the
what these bacteria would do is that
their waste product product was oxygen
they would excrete
oxygen into the atmosphere as a waste
product
and they proliferated so much in the
oceans of the world
that they ended up
giving out so much oxygen that the
entire
composition of the atmosphere was
changed and oxygen became one of the
primary components of the atmosphere
this is called the great oxygenation
event
or the great oxygenation catastrophe
because oxygen was a poison to all other
species
to most of the species on the planet at
the time and it caused a mass extinction
and
most of the species on the planet at
that time at the time died out because
of this enormous amount of oxygen that
suddenly came into the atmosphere
so oxygen was a poison
at the time
even today
we can tolerate about 21 percent oxygen
or oxygen in the atmosphere
the rest of it about 7 more than 70
percent is nitrogen
almost 79
so we are accustomed we are used we have
evolved in such a manner that we are
used to breathing
about 78 79 nitrogen and 20 21 oxygen
right and nitrogen is something that we
don't use but that's how it is
now if we were to have a more
oxygen-rich atmosphere we don't quite
know what the uh consequences of that
could be
there is something called oxygen
poisoning when you breathe in too much
oxygen when people are given pure oxygen
to breathe i think it it can have
harmful effects to the to the human
physiology
and i'm sure it would be harmful to
other species as well if you would raise
the
level of the oxygen so the entire
environment is an ecosystem
it's in a very delicate balance
and
all of the species on the planet have
evolved over millions of years
in response to this to this balance of
various gases and all that in the
atmosphere and the kind of temperature
that we have
you change any of these parameters it's
going to cause
a large scale effects and this could be
very harmful effects you could end up
causing a mass extinction if you pump
out so much additional oxygen
into the atmosphere
so
it's not a good idea you cannot play god
and start tinkering with the composition
of the atmosphere and the planet and all
that it's a very very very bad idea
right so that's what i have to say
soham says i'm considering taking
computer science engineering
for college but recently i heard that
gpt3 and vs code assistant ai
can predict code for a given problem and
automatically generate possible
algorithms taking into consideration
that ai will advance in the next 5-10
years
is my future career option software
development engineering in danger of
being of getting replaced
by an ai in artificial intelligence
so yes we have reached the stage
where ai can write code
when we have reached the stage where ai
can improve upon its own code and get
better iteratively we have reached there
so
the question is this
when we write code when we create
algorithms
when we create new software products and
packages we are essentially
trying to solve certain problems
that's what all the softwares do that's
what all the algorithms do we are trying
to solve problems we are trying to
improve upon
whatever we have right
that's what software development
engineering is all about it's about
solving real world problems
and
how do we know there are problems
because we have eyes ears and we can see
what's what the world is like
now when it comes to an ai
an ai does not have access to all of
this data what's out there in the world
do we have potholes on the street
do people need pizza delivery in 20
minutes or 10 minutes ai doesn't know
any of these things ai can only sense
certain things
as long as they are given that it is
given that much sensory input and then
whatever it perceives as problems it
tries to solve that
so ai's have reached the stage
where they can
solve what they perceive as problems and
improve upon their own code and get
better
on their own volition
but yet
ai is not capable of as of today
understanding what problems human human
beings face
and what solutions we human beings need
right it's not at that stage i don't i
don't
imagine
that ai will reach there in the next 10
20 30 years
uh ai is to solve problems it needs
inputs it needs data as to what the
world is like now ai doesn't have visual
data it doesn't have
sensory inputs the way we have what are
our senses we have eyes
so we see the world and then we can see
the problems we can hear things which
adds to this data that we have
so all of these senses the five senses
they tell us what the world is like and
what the problems are
and there are very human problems that
we face
ai doesn't have eyes and ears
so air doesn't really know what the
world is like
it's like a bunch of bacteria sitting in
a petri dish
wondering what's out there but they
don't have the senses to tell them that
there's a human being looking at them
right now under a microscope
so similarly ai is handicapped
in a variety of ways
and ai doesn't have access to all of
this information and that's why ai
cannot solve the problems that we face
maybe in 20 30 40 years we may be able
to have ais that
have access to such things in which case
we are doomed essentially
so that's where we are
i don't think that your future career
option is in danger of getting replaced
by a ai in the next 10 or 20 years
that's my personal assessment so i think
your career is
thus far safe
but yeah we are going towards that in
that direction the ais are learning on
their own now and they can actually
improve upon themselves and write their
own code and possibly they could write
programs that do other things as well
but they are still not at the stage
where they can actually solve problems
that people face and society faces
akash says we can explain the world
without the need of a creator
many scientists claim this to support
their argument of why they are an
atheist
doesn't this contradict the fact that we
know nothing about the universe
considering the vast amount of mysteries
and paradoxes that emerge out of the
study of physics
does being a scientist necessitate being
an atheist
so in science it's about uh the most
parsimonious
explanations of various things
and it's all about the physical universe
and observational data and empirical
data
it's about
the observable universe
it's about the physical world
and material world and physical
phenomena
so god
is something that
is not measurable quantifiable
verifiable falsifiable and that's why
god doesn't exist
in science
the concept of god is unscientific
and when i say unscientific it doesn't
mean it's bad or evil
or primitive or regressive it it means
it falls outside of the realm of science
that's all it is
so yeah the aim of science is to
explain the world through purely
physical phenomena that's all it is
that's the aim of science the aim of
philosophy is something quite different
the aim of
theology or religion or spirituality is
entirely different these things cannot
mix
philosophy is
science is a subset of philosophy
spirituality i don't know what it is we
don't even have a def proper definition
of what that is and so on
uh
so yeah we know next to nothing about
the universe it doesn't mean that we
need to bring in supernatural
or or unphysical phenomena into the
realm of science
it doesn't mean that
we have
an enormous amount of mysteries 95
percent of the universe is dark
right and we don't know what it is
so yeah we we do have we do face the
problem
but we cannot
the moment we we start mixing things
from outside into science it's no longer
science
that's how it is
so
science is completely separate from
things like religion and god and ethics
and philosophy it doesn't mean that
scientists have to be atheists
there are plenty of scientists who are
very very much not atheists
i can give you some very good examples
georges lumet
one of the major uh
the the guy who came up
with the
he's one of the major uh figures in
cosmology he was a
catholic priest
yeah he came up i think with the
expansion of the universe if i'm not
mistaken
and that goes against all all tenets of
catholicism that's an example
closer to home we had
srinivasa
one of the greatest mathematicians of
all time
he was profoundly religious
right
um
what about uh
what's his name
ecg sudarsan
ekumar chandi george the sudarshan he
was born into a christian family in
india
later he became a hindu
and he lived and died as a hindu
he is one of the greatest physicists of
all time he should have give he should
have won three nobel prizes
he was awarded none which is all
politics
he was very much a hindu he was very
much a believer in god or whatever it is
right that he believed in
he was religious
so you don't have
to be an atheist to be a scientist
absolutely not
but when you do science you don't bring
in you don't mix up
things that don't don't believe belong
in science that's all i'm saying
so you don't have to be an atheist to be
a scientist and it's a
it's a misconception
that most scientists are atheist
there are certain
scientists who i do not consider to be
high quality scientists
who say
that human emotions are a bunch of
chemical reactions and blah blah blah
blah blah it's all chemical reactions
and physical reactions and that's all
life is and that's all emotions are and
that's all everything is
such people
well these are not very high quality
scientists okay these people
that's all i would say about them i'm
not taking any names of fyi right but
yeah one comes across these people
so uh the truth is we know nothing
and there could be explanations that are
way beyond science it's possible but as
scientists you need to be disciplined
and you need to follow the scientific
method which is about physical phenomena
physical objects and
um
and physical evidence
right empirical evidence so that's what
it is but you don't have to be an
atheist to be a scientist absolutely not
okay swapnil says what kind of celestial
body is a rocot
okay let me show you what arocot is
so the new horizons uh spacecraft
which uh did a flyby of the last
unphotographed uh planet pluto
uh
it went for it it is now going further
out into into outer space
and it subsequently did a flyby of a
trans-neptunian object called which is
now called arrow costs or whatever
so let me show you what it looks like
it's an object called a contact binary
so as you can see it is an object which
has two components two lobes so to say
right
and it is classified as a contact binary
so it is essentially two
uh bodies two two rocky objects
that uh somehow came into contact not
violently it was not a massive violent
collision it was a soft contact which
happened slowly
and then they just fused together or
they because of gravitation they have
stuck together and now it's just one
object with two
separate
uh distinct lobes
so this is an actual image of that
object arrow koth
also called ultima tool or whatever
and this image was taken by uh new
horizons by the new horizons spacecraft
so it is way out there
in the caper belt
right
so this is the path that the new
horizons spacecraft has taken
and uh
it's on the way that it found
it made a fi did a flyby of this object
and it took its photograph
so this is the photograph of pluto one
of the photographs of pluto that it took
and it's moon
charon
and also arakat
so that is what arakat arakat is it is a
trans-neptunian object
and it is a contact binary it's a binary
object which came into existence by
from the contact of two separate
objects
or asteroids
okay pranit says what are your views on
blockchain cryptocurrency and web 3.0
will it disrupt disrupt the world
it will certainly disrupt the world
so we had web 1.0 then we have now web
2.0 and we are going towards web 3.0 web
1.0 was a static internet you could go
and visit a website but you could not
interact with it
these are just static pages html css and
that's it
that's web 1.0 so the old web then you
had web 2.0 in which you had interactive
websites wordpress right you could go to
a website and type comments then you
have social media in which you can do
likes and dislikes and thumbs up and you
can respond and you can tweet
your facebook in which you can upload
videos and you can
write texts and posts and all that you
have google search engine and all that
this is the interactive web the web
you have uh
online banking systems and all that you
can log into your bank account and do
transactions
so all of this is web 2.0 the
interactive
web
web 3.0 so the one of the features of
the interactive
web
uh web210 is that it is centralized
all of your information is centralized
and stored in servers that belong to
various entities
so
every time you uh create you have you
want to use a website you have to create
an account typically you give out
personal information and they store your
personal information and they
essentially mine your information and
use it for various purposes for they
monetize it they commercialize it
so that is the
uh
one of the major salient features of web
2.0
that your information
becomes the property of big corporations
typically in silicon valley
that's what it is
web 3.0 is the decentralized internet
it's based on the blockchain technology
which
ensures that your your information is
is given out on a need to know basis you
don't have to give out all kinds of
private or personal information
only what is required for a certain
transaction you have to give out so
that's the blockchain
technology that underpins web 3.0 it's
still in the very nascent formative
stage
you have cryptocurrency you have certain
software
software's on built on top of that like
ethereum
which is a software solution
then you have
things like nfts you know non-fungible
tokens and things like that so we are
still in the very infancy of web 3.0
and they
even web 3.0 as of today is not quite
decentralized even today much of this is
centralized in silicon valley
yeah much of it is owned by various uh
very wealthy people
ethereum for instance yeah it's it's not
quite decentralized even the polygon
network is based is built upon ethereum
which is
a certain kind of blockchain which is
not decentralized it's actually owned by
someone
so to say
so we are still in the infancy of this
but yes eventually it will disrupt the
world
and right now we are witnessing the
cryptocurrency crash there's a overall
recession coming
what looks like a recession is coming
right now and the cryptocurrencies have
crashed bitcoin went below 20 thousand
dollars for the first time and god knows
how long
i don't know what the current status is
i'm not keeping track of it because i'm
good thankfully
but yeah people have lost lots of money
uh nfts are now cold
it was a very hot market just a couple
of months ago now empties have gone down
so
yeah we are witnessing possibly the
bursting of a bubble
which may be a good thing in the long
run well we we had the
the the um
dot com crash
in the late at the very end of the 28th
century in the late 1990s in which you
know which was a
much needed
uh
change that needed that had to come in
the internet so people said the internet
is gone because of the dot com crash but
that's not quite the case we as it's
still here
similarly blockchain will be there
it will underpin things like smart
contracts which are
trustless permissionless contracts in
which you don't need to trust somebody
and things like that
so it will eventually become a major
thing it will
disrupt the world
and eventually all kinds of contracts
could be
done in solidity
you know on blockchain
and you don't need to trust anybody
for executing such contracts
house deeds sales of houses and
apartments
and god knows even the
uh corporate contracts lots of things
could happen
on the blockchain so that may be the
future we may we may be going towards
possibly
so it's still early days
but eventually i believe it will be a
major thing
maybe in the next five to ten years
definitely
okay a couple of questions cosmicality
says if colors are different wavelengths
of light
then what are black and white colors
and
crazy brain says my question is that if
we see colors and objects based on the
light that is reflected from the
surfaces then how do the objects
actually look
are they black in color or white or
something else also if we see for
example a flower pot
the shape and color that we interpret of
the pot is the actual light reflected by
it or the light that our eyes are able
to receive
these are very interesting questions
deep questions
um
somewhat philosophical tools to a
certain extent
so
yeah
colors
what are colors
so
we perceive colors
when our eyes see light
so light comes in a variety of colors
right that's how we see it
there is red light there is brown well
yeah
what light is this is this red it's
reddish right this this curtain here
you have books of all kinds of colors
yellow blue
there is dark something black black and
white orange and so on we perceive a
whole range of colors
through our eyes
and when there is no light there is no
color it's just black
so first of all let's talk about white
and black
black is the absence of light
black is not really a color it's an
absence of light so when you have
something that is black in color it
means that the surface of that object
absorbs all light and reflects nothing
back that's why it appears to us to be
black
right
for instance uh this this thing here
the tip of my microphone it appears
black
which means it's made up of a substance
that absorbs
all of the light or most of the light
and reflects almost nothing back
that's why it appears black what is
white white is
a white object like whatever we have
here
is something
that reflects lights of light of all
frequencies away it absorbs almost
nothing
and when you add up all the frequencies
of light all the wavelengths you get
white light
white light is essentially
a mixture of all the different colors of
light
so that is white and that is black black
is something that absorbs everything and
and reflects no light that's why it
appears black and white is the exact
opposite of black which means it is a
substance or a surface that reflects
everything
all different
wavelengths
of light so that's why it appears white
now what is light what what is color
actually
so
color
is what our mind perceives
when it sees light of a certain
wavelength or frequency
frequency is the inverse of the
wavelength right
so when you get
when
a certain when light of a certain
frequency comes into our eyes
our mind interprets at it as a certain
color
so for instance this is red
it has a certain distinctive frequency
and when my eye sees that
my brain or my mind interprets that as
the red color
certain frequencies appear
yellow certain appear blue
and so on
this color
is an illusion
it's just something our mind makes up
to help us make sense of the world
the actual world
the actual reality of the world that's
around us is way more complex
it is so complex that we can't make
sense of it in real time
so our mind our brain simplifies the
world for us
by giving various frequencies colors
for instance if you have a cell phone
yeah
when you when you take a cell phone
and you see the interface
you see all the all the different apps
and all that yeah
you see apps and you see various
readings you can do texts and you can do
emails and all that you can pick up
phone calls and respond to phone calls
and all that
inside the phone
all of this data all of this information
is stored and represented in the form
of voltages and circuits
so if you had
to toggle a bunch of voltages and
fiddle with circuits in order to send an
email
or to send a text message
you would never be able to do it because
it's so complicated
so what the gui of your phone does is
that it gives you a very simplified
presentation of what the actual
complexity is
similarly our mind gives us a very
simplified image of what the real world
is the real world is very different from
what it appears to be
what we see is an illusion
you know the concept of maya
it is a real thing
the real world is incredibly complex
the real world is quantum in nature
you have superv superpositions and d
coherence happening all the time
you have entanglement
entanglement possibly gives rise to time
who knows
the real world is incredibly complicated
and for us for our mind to be able to
decipher that in real time
would be impossible it would overload
our mind
and it would ensure it would
ensure that we would not survive because
we are just trying to make sense of
what's happening and we can't respond to
the world
so
to mitigate this problem our minds
simplify the world for us
and they represent all these complicated
wavelengths and frequencies in terms of
simple colors
and certain colors don't even exist
pink
the pink color
does not exist there is no frequency or
wavelength for pink
and yet we see pink
it is a non-spectral color
it doesn't exist on the spectrum you
know what is the spectrum the rainbow
the web gear that you were taught in
school
yeah violet indigo blue yellow
green whatever right
that is the frequent that's the spectrum
the color spectrum there is no pink in
that
and yet we perceive pink there is no
white in that we perceive white there is
no gray in that
we perceive gray there is no brown in
that but we perceive it so many of these
colors that we apparently see
don't even exist these are non-spectral
colors
and that's the trick the minds our minds
play on us
just to ensure our survival
so that simplifies the world for us
so that that is uh an insight into the
weirdness
of the world you know
so that's how it is
santosh says what are your views on
immortality is it possible to achieve
the same
so immortality means the absence of
death you never die
so in in mythology in folklore etc we
have things like uh
nosferatu the vampire the vampire never
dies right
immortal creature and of course we have
a
certain in indian uh mythology so to say
some people will be offended if i call
it mythology we have the the uh
the immortals right like ashwathama etc
so yeah we we have the concept of
immortality that some people never die
and all that
but is it a real thing
well i have never seen anybody who's
immortal
none of us has seen someone who is
right
uh
and as far as we know from all the data
that we have from all the evidence that
we have immortality doesn't seem to be a
thing but but but there are there are
caveats
you go
you drill under the earth's surface
many kilometers down
you're gonna bring up core samples of
rock of rock
that is hundreds of millions of years
old all right
and what you find
is that there are bacteria in there
in this rock that is hundreds of
millions of years old
and these bacteria have been entombed in
that rock for that long
and they possibly went into a dormant
state
and yet they survived
and when you bring this rock out these
bacteria come back to life
so when it is when it comes to bacteria
they seem to have this property of
near immortality i mean a hundred
million years is and if you if if an
organism survives a hundred million
years
that is more or less immortal
so it obviously survives in
for this long in suspended animation of
some kind
it's not actually evolving or
reproducing or anything it's just
existing
it's frozen so to say
it goes into hibernation of some kind
but it does survive
so yeah bacteria seem to have this
property
of almost of near immortality
but
higher
beings like
multicellular organisms may not have it
and definitely
large animals
do not
have the property of immortality we have
a certain lifespan lifespan that's built
into us
as we grow older
the the the telomeres at the ends of our
chromosomes they deteriorate they
shorten and that seems to have uh the
aging of the effect of aging right
so typically a huge the average lifespan
of a human being
it depends from country to country but
typically the higher limit is about 100
100 years 110 maybe yeah that sort of
thing
so
immortality doesn't seem to be a thing
now imagine
imagine hypothetically you make somebody
immortal right
is that person really going to be
immortal from
the identity perspective
because
even if the body is immortal
will the mind
survive that long
people who get older
uh their cognitive faculties decline
right
they have trouble remembering events
their mental acuity and sharpness
undergoes a decline even someone like
the president of one of the most
powerful countries in the world is in
clear cognitive decline
so as human beings get older their
mental faculties deteriorate
their memory
deteriorates
and
it's possible that there is a certain
limit to the amount of memories you can
store in your mind in your brain
and if you go beyond that you may have
to
uh overwrite old memories to create new
ones
so let's say you keep a person alive
somehow for 200 years
and the the memory capacity capacity
let's say
is memories of 100 years so after 100
years the person will experience new new
events and
he or she will form new memories
will it not happen that these new
memories will overwrite the old memories
of when the person was young and the
child and all that
and if the person lives 200 years
their entire personality may change and
all the memories of the past may be gone
and only new memories may be available
so the question is will the person
remain the same person or will this be a
totally different person
these are questions
that arise when you talk about
immortality
right so
from a biological perspective for human
human beings and other animals it's
definitely not possible
from all the data and evidence that we
have you want to believe stories and all
that's your choice
from the perspective of evidence there
is no evidence that immortality is a
thing so yeah it's it's as of today not
possible
okay karun says is there any way
or possibility to convert ocean water
into drinking water if yes then what is
the current status of this project
and who is working on this
see if if something is possible it
doesn't mean it's a project
it doesn't
necessitate that somebody is working on
it so let's address the question of is
it possible or not to convert ocean
water into drinking water and yes it is
definitely possible
there's a process called desalination
it's very simple
excuse me
you take ocean water
in a let's say you can do it yourself at
home
if you have the right equipment
you take
a pot or a pan in which you put ocean
water you boil it
and whatever vapor comes out you collect
it and you condense it in a different
vessel
right
and
at the end of this process
all the salt and impurities will be left
behind in the in the vessel in which you
are heating
and the distilled purified water
will be collected in the other vessel
that's the process of distillation
that's uh that's how you purify ocean
water and desalinate it
uh
you know how they make wine out of
grapes
they collect a bunch of grapes maybe 100
kilos 200 kilos they put them in a
massive giant vessel a vat
and then they ask children or even
adults to go and stomp on it
either wearing boots or even barefoot
that sounds very disgusting because
boots are dirty and feet are also dirty
right if you go barefoot and do all that
you do that in the afternoon you're
gonna sweat into that it sounds terrible
so what they do is they do this whole
process for they do the mashing for a
couple of hours stomping on it
barefoot or with boots on so
what what emerges after after this is
that you have the grapes have been
transformed into mush
into mush grape juice and pulp and all
that then they leave that to ferment for
a certain amount of time few days months
what i don't know what the time period
is
so it ferments in this formation of
alcohol and then this alcohol the vessel
that contains alcohol is heated
the alcohol evaporates it is collected
in a different vessel it is distilled
and then it is allowed to condense again
and that's how you get pure
alcohol without any impurities whatever
so that's how they make wine that's the
simplified process
similarly a similar process can be used
for purifying sea water a very similar
process
desalination and there are multiple
different ways of
doing this process
more energy efficient ways are available
i think israel is one of the pioneers in
desalination technology
so you do this and the output is what
they call brine which is very
concentrated sea water
and
that's something that you dump back into
the ocean and it's not going to cause
any real problems because it's something
that comes comes out of the ocean anyway
so that is called desalination you can
convert ocean water into drinking water
through reverse osmosis or through
various other things also we can do this
right
so yeah that's what it is
and israel is one of the pioneers in
this technology um
and i believe they had in at some point
in time
offered to uh
offered this technology to india as well
so i don't know what happened whether we
took them up on this thing or not
israel is a very dry arid place of
course in case you know
so they would certainly need something
like that to
for their water drinking water
requirements
in the case of india we have lots of
rivers and all that so we may not need
it to that extent but it's always good
to have the technology
so is there a project or not i am not
aware the israelis do it we in india i'm
not sure if we have any
desalination plants that do this thing
with ocean water but it's certainly
feasible
okay kane shaq chauhan says what is cold
fusion reaction
is it really just theory or is it
possible can it mimic conventional
fusion or fission for let's say on a
smaller scale
okay
what is cold fusion to understand what
is cold fusion let's first go into what
is fusion what is nuclear fusion nuclear
fusion
conceptually
is when you take two atoms or nuclei
of a certain element
and you fuse them together
you take to nuclear you fuse them
together
or maybe you shoot them
at each other at very high velocities
so high the velocity should be so high
that it it overcomes the electrostatic
repulsion of the nuclei
and these two nuclear nuclei collide
they merge together and they fuse
together and that
gives off an enormous amount of energy
that in brief is what fusion is
typically you would do it with helium he
helium fusion hydrogen fusion whatever
right so that's what we do
so to do this you have to overcome the
electrostatic repulsion of the nuclei
a nucleus in case you know is a
positively charged object
the nucleus of an atom has a positive
charge
around it you have electrons going
around which have a negative charge and
that balances it balances out and the
atom is overall
electrically neutral
okay
so
nuclei have a positive charge
now as you i hope you know like charges
repel
opposite charges attract so a positive
charge is attracted towards a negative
charge but if you have two positive
charges they repel each other
the closer you bring them together the
more they repel each other that's the
repulsive force
the ripples of electrostatic force right
so um to bring two
nuclei together to bring them in contact
would require very high amounts of
energy which means that the two nuclei
need to be shot at each other at very
high speeds
so typically what you would do
is you
create a state of matter called a plasma
which is a very high temperature
and high velocity
form of matter
and because the velocities of these
atoms these nuclei are so high there
would be collisions between them and
they would fuse together and that's how
you get a fusion reaction
so the
faster
the higher the velocity of a nucleus is
the hotter it is said to be
a gas is hot when its molecules are
moving very fast at high velocities a
gas is cold when its molecules are
moving at slow velocities
so plasma in which you have
nuclei
at that are moving at very high
velocities is called a hot plasma
and if you have fusion that happens in
this environment it's hot fusion
so typically you would use something
like a toca mac what's it talk about let
me show you what it is
aqua mac is
a device in which you could create a
fusion reaction it's a machine
so you use magnetic confinement to to
confine the plasma within the
boundary
of the torquamac this is what it looks
like
all right so use you use magnetic
confinement to create to to confine the
plasma and ensure that it doesn't leak
out of the walls of this of this machine
and hopefully you can
have plasma that is energetic enough to
have high velocity
high energy collisions and you could
possibly have fusion reactions
through this
so that is the hope that we have and
that would be hot fusion
fusion at very high velocities and
temperatures
what is cold fusion
it is a hypothetical
form of fusion
in which you can do this without going
at high velocities and high temperatures
so let's say you have a glass of
whatever it is on your table top and if
you can achieve fusion in that
without heating it up that is cold
fusion
so in the past some people have made
claims that they've achieved cold fusion
but they it's never been verified they
have never been able to prove it or
demonstrate it
so those claims have turned out to be
hoaxes
right so that is the difference between
hot fusion and cold fusion fusion is the
holy grail
fusion gives off way more energy than
fission
and efficient can be controlled in
nuclear reactors hopefully in the future
we will have fusion reactors fusion is
clean
there is no radioactive
uh waste material that comes out of
fusion fission reactions give off
radioactive waste you need to do
something with that you need to dispose
of it in a manner that doesn't destroy
the environment it's dangerous fission
reactions are dangerous fusion
gives you much more energy and it's way
cleaner
so that's why fusion is the future but
we should be able to achieve it so as of
today there is absolutely no way in
which we could achieve cold fusion it's
just a dream right now
maybe in a hundred years maybe we may
have technology or we may have we we may
have miniaturized talker max that are
like you could actually hold in your
hand possibly
who knows
but as of today it's not possible as of
today cold fusion is not possible as of
today we have not even
uh been able to create a sustained
fusion reaction on our planet
so it's a work in progress but hopefully
it will happen sometime soon
okay samhita says if the law of
conservation of matter is true then is
the big bang theory acceptable because
that would mean that matter had been
created
and will be destroyed someday and that
violates the universal law
so what is the big bang theory
the big bang theory says that
about 13.8 or so billion years before
today
all of the
matter and energy that is present in the
observable and non-observable universe
all of that was concentrated
in a small infinite infinitesimally
small
point
right
and somehow all of that expanded space
time expanded and that was the so-called
big bang and that gave rise to the to
the universe that we observe around us
today
so what it says
is that all of this matter and energy
was already there
it was concentrated
in
a small point
an almost infinitely dense point
so it was not created it was already
there
and in the future if there is a big
crunch
which i spoke about in the last episode
all of that will come back together
again into another singularity
so this this point in which everything
was concentrated is called a singularity
right so nothing was created nothing was
destroyed
all of the energy and matter matter
energy equal to mc squared all of the
energy that was present in that initial
singularity
which was at the birth of the big bang
all of that is there today nothing has
been created nothing has been destroyed
so
matter energy mass energy is conserved
there is no creation of destruction
so that's how it is nothing has been
created to destroy and nothing has been
violated
okay they just says why is it said that
we can never travel with speed more than
the speed of light why is the upper
limit the speed of flight
is it not a close-minded approach
um
we don't believe that it's like that
it's the equations of physics that tell
us
when you
accelerate
an
object
because of the
effects of relativity relativistic
effects
the mass of that object increases
and if you want to
accelerate an object
to a speed that is close to the speed of
light you have to impart an enormous
amount of energy
to it
and the effect is that that object
becomes more and more massive
and to accelerate an object to the speed
of light
the equations tell us
that you would have to impart an
infinite amount of energy to it
and we don't have
an infinite amount of energy anywhere
that's why it's impossible to
accelerate something to the speed of
light
and more than the speed of light is a
whole different story and it's not
physically physically possible
so it's not like we have decided all of
us together all the scientists that this
is how it's going to be we have decided
that nobody can travel to the speed of
light or more than the speed of light
and because we say it that's the law
it's not like that
we have deduced the laws of physics from
experimental
and observational evidence from
observing the patterns of the universe
and the best theory that we have is the
general theory of relativity which tells
us all these things and this theory has
been tested hundreds of times thousands
of times if the objective of these tests
is to falsify the theory is to prove it
wrong
scientists have been trying for the past
100 years to prove this theory wrong
and every single attempt has failed
that's why we believe it it's not like
we believe
it tells us what it is what what the
world is like what the universe is like
and because we are not able to prove it
wrong we have to accept
these equations
so it's not a closed-minded approach
it's a scientific approach
science is not about belief
i believe i can fly so i can fly it's
not like that you see
so it's not a closed-minded approach
it's the scientific method at work here
we cannot
i mean
if people want to believe that you can
travel at the speed of light fine
believe it
i i wish you all the best in your
attempt to travel the speed of light
won't happen right
so that's how it is it's not about
belief it's not about being close-minded
i am an open minded person
you cannot be a good scientist
unless you are really open-minded
right so that's how it is it's it's
paradoxical but that's how it is
rtk says is there something left for
science to discover other than the
external universe and quantum mechanics
and time and gravity too
there's a whole lot for science left for
science to discover we know nothing
we know next to nothing
we only i i i may sound like a broken
record now i've said this so many times
i don't know how many times i've said
this
we only understand
we only see
five percent of the universe 95 of the
universe is dark it is unseen it is un
unknown we don't understand it
95 of the universe is unknown to us
there is a whole lot for us to discover
and even that five person that we know
or we can see or perceive we don't even
understand that very well
there may be cracks appearing in the
standard model of physics right now
based on new experimental evidence so
there's a whole lot left to discover
we know of four forces who knows there
may be more forces out there that we are
not aware of
there may be more dimensions out there
that we may not be aware of compactified
dimensions
who knows
there's a whole universe out there there
could be whole dark universe out there
right now there could be a whole bunch
of dark physicists wondering
what the
missing five percent of the universe is
like who knows
so there's a whole lot left to discover
and that's why physics and science is so
exciting
exasperated pharagos says
if intelligent life
a billion light years away
so earth through a telescope would they
see
earth how it was a billion years ago and
have no idea that it presently exists
yes
light is not uh does not travel at an
instantaneous speed
it travels at 300 000 meters per second
three lakh meters per second
right
uh so
it travels a certain distance in one
year and that's called that distance is
called a light year
so if a galaxy is a billion light years
away from us
and they are looking at the earth from a
telescope
then they will see the light
that left the earth a billion years
before ago
so when you're looking into space when
you're looking at the night sky you are
looking back in time
let's say you're looking at the
andromeda galaxy
which is about 1.5 million light years
from here i believe
so if you have a powerful telescope
looking at it you're seeing it what
happened 1.5 million years before today
you're not seeing what's happening there
right now
and if you're observing you know a
galaxy that is 5 billion light years
from here
you're witnessing something that
happened five billion years ago
and similarly for them if they are
looking at us and they are one five
billion
light years away
they are seeing what happened here
five billion years ago
which would be the protostellar disc or
the
before the birth of the solar system so
that's how it is so looking out into
space is essentially looking back in
time
akash is which is your favorite and less
least favorite branch of physics out of
all these quantum physics nuclear
physics astrophysics
mechanics thermodynamics electricity
magnetism plasma physics electrical
electronics chemical physics solid state
physics why and why not why not
my favorite branches are quantum and
astrophysics
thermodynamics also interesting
uh electromagnetism is also reasonably
interesting
my least favorite branches are
electronics electrical
whatever
chemical physics
nuclear physics very boring and solid
state physics yeah
uh why why not
i've i am
drawn towards mystery
um
if i had not been a physicist maybe i
would have been a detective because i am
drawn towards mysteries
and there is nothing mysterious about
electrical physics or electronics
anymore there's nothing new to discover
chemical physics is
there's no intrigue in it there's no
nothing that fascinates you there's no
big discoveries to be made right
um astrophysics is interesting because
we don't know what's out there that's
fascinating that that's something that
drives your curiosity
quantum physics hey there's a whole lot
to discover we don't know what the world
is like what why are things the way they
are and what is quantum physics trying
to tell us
no one's able to agree
there could be really mysterious
interpretations i mean really strange
interpretations the many worlds
interpretation and various other things
so these are the foundations of physics
this is what will drive physics forward
and will give us the new next
breakthroughs
dark matter dark energy quantum physics
that's that's what really intrigues me
so that's why it's because i am
fascinated by mystery i want to solve
big problems
i don't want to
work on something that everyone already
knows about
i mean what's left to discover in
nuclear physics
what's left to discover in electronics
so that's why
dungeon johan says why does venus spin
in the clockwise direction
okay
so all
most of the uh planets
in the solar system they have a certain
direction
of spin
on the earth the sun
rises in the east and sets in the west
the same goes for mars
the same goes for most of the planets
and they all rotate at a certain speed
different different different speeds
when it comes to venus
the sun rises in the west
and sets in the east
that's how it rotates
in the opposite direction and one day
one full rotation on venus
takes nearly nearly roughly one earth
here close to one earth here more than
300 days
more than 300 earth days
that's how slow it rotates why is it so
that's that's a big mystery that nobody
quite knows why it is so
so
it's not just venus that's like this i
think even uranus or neptune i think
it's uranus that's like whose axis of
rotation is tilted
98 degrees or so
um
so one of the reasons why something like
this would happen is because of ancient
collisions with other objects
so
if a planet suffers a collision
with another large object maybe another
ancient planet
then the axis of rotation could be
changed it was
spinning in this manner like this and
suddenly it goes in the opposite manner
because of the because of the massive
impact
in whatever glancing manner which it
happened so that is one possibility
the other possibility is that uh
certain
atmospheric phenomena on venus
slowly uh changed the direction of
rotation so as we know venus has a very
very thick
and massive atmosphere
and
possibly certain phenomena and that most
in the atmosphere could have changed the
direction of the spin of venus so it was
spinning just like the earth spins but
slowly slowly slowly the spin slowed
down
stopped all together and then it started
spinning in the opposite direction which
could possibly explain why the spin is
so slow and why
a full rotation takes more than 300
earth days
that could possibly explain it when it
comes to uranus which is tilted in a
mysterious fashion it could be an
ancient impact
with some other ancient planet which no
longer exists that is a possibility so
these are the reasons why such things
can happen but we don't have the exact
answers but we have a range of answers
which can explain this phenomenon
how to reach the full potential of the
human brain
a jee aspirant here
i would say that you need to
optimize what you do with your brain
don't waste time don't waste time on
things that are not important
um
see the human brain has us
needs sleep you know that
typically eight hours of sleep so you
have 16 hours of time left
so to optimize the potential of the
human brain of your brain
use those 16 hours wisely
uh use those 16 hours in a way that
takes you forward in whatever direction
you want to achieve
and that's by doing time management
energy management and
not wasting your time on unnecessary and
unimportant things
so yeah that's how we would you would do
it i mean i don't have the
the
the silver bullet the panacea that you
do this and everything be your full
potential will be unlocked
i don't think i have unlocked the full
potential of my brain i don't think it's
possible to fully unlocked and com fully
unlock and completely optimize the
functioning of any person's brain but
you can come close if you
if you prioritize the most important uh
work and tasks that you would want to do
in a day
some people make these long to do lists
15 16 things to do in one day it's not
possible to
work well that way
uh one of the most important concepts is
deep work
deep work is something your brain is
capable of doing maybe three or four
hours in a day
there is like
work at a very high level of focus and
concentration
for that you would need to cut off
distractions close the door keep all the
people out make sure no one disturbs you
switch off the phone or keep it in a
different room and focus on what take
what is going to take you forward
for three or four hours that's called
deep work so that is one of the core
concepts of of
of progress
and
optimizing the way you work
so it's a it's a
it's a bouquet of things that you can do
and everybody is different so you need
to find what works best for you so
yeah
okay alpha beta says uh
my question is related to my career i
want to remaster my 10th 11th standard
math physics chemistry
show series books you mentioned but more
of academic your one minute will be very
helpful
okay you want to remaster your 10th 11th
standard math physics chemistry i don't
know what standard you're in now but
maybe it's a couple of years before
so may
let's say hypothetically you're in the
12th and you want to remaster 10th and
11th level math physics chemistry
to do that i would suggest i mean i
don't know how much time you have and
all that assuming you have a lot of time
i'm assuming you have sufficient time
if you want to remastered your 10
standard math
go back to the 8th standard level and
and fix all the deficiencies you may
have there
eight standard nightstand then come to
the 10 standard level
because if you want to be
really good at math at a certain level
you need to ensure that the foundation
that comes before that is perfect
so first go back even before the 10th
standard level and
and ensure that everything all the all
the concepts are crystal clear
and you're able to solve all the
problems and all that so it's it's a
process and the only way
to master mathematics is to solve lots
and lots and lots of problems so many
problems that you can do in your sleep
i remember when i was
in the 11 standard maybe
and uh i was i was i had come across
calculus for the first time somewhere
around that time i don't know which
standard it was
and uh
there was a time when i was kind of
struggling with integration integrity
casualness so all i did was solve
hundreds and hundreds of problems day in
and day out
and there came a town time
i solved i was solving so many problems
i saw everything as an integration
problem so i was i was going somewhere
on my bicycle then there was a pothole
on the road
i looked at the pothole and i asked the
first thought that came to my mind
was how am i going to solve this plot
pothole am i going to integrate it by
parts
or am i going to use some trigonometric
substitution
so that's how i was seeing everything
you have to solve so many problems that
it becomes second nature
so that's how you do it
there are no shortcuts
the
only thing i would recommend is
a lot of hard work
all the best
okay harsh says pteroscope telescope
turning earth into a giant telescope is
it a feasible technology you saw an
explanation by a scientist who's working
on this concept
paper etc on youtube
i believe the terrascope concept is that
you use the earth as a giant focusing
lens
so the earth has an atmosphere that has
a certain thickness
and the atmosphere refracts light
so you use this property of the
atmosphere
to refract light and you place a
telescope or or
or a mirror or something at a certain
distance away from the earth which would
be typically the earth moon kind of
distance
where all the light is focused
and that's how you can study distant
objects so it has certain pro certain
cons and
you can only see what is right directly
between you
a bit behind the earth wherever your
your instrument is located so it has
certain limitations but it could give
you very clear images of certain objects
and so on so that is the telescope thing
it is
something that could possibly happen in
the future it's not something that has
already been implemented it's
something that can work it's a
theoretical thing as of today but it's
possible it can be done
avilash says is there
if there is a multiverse what occupies
the space in between the universes we
don't know
we don't even know if there's a
multiverse if there is a multiverse
which hypothetically is possible but we
can't falsify it we can't prove it so
it's like beyond science but in case
there's a multiverse view who knows
what's between the the universes let's
say each universe is like a ball
so what's between these balls we don't
know there could be maybe nothing
maybe there could be
rainbows and unicorns and ice cream i
don't know we have no idea of knowing
there is no answer
there is no answer that can be either
proven
or falsified
so
so i don't have the answer sorry nobody
has the answer nobody at all
okay i think i'm done with today's
questions let let's take a few questions
from the live live chat
someone is saying vacuum i mean how do
you define vacuum
vacuum itself exists inside space time
right
think about it
vacuum
is something that exists inside space
time and vacuum itself is not empty
vacuum is steaming
it is teaming
with particle anti-particle pairs
right the quantum form
so that's not quite what would be within
between universes
vacuum itself requires space time
but at the end if if our universe has an
edge or an end space time itself ends
over there so what's beyond
that is the question
right so take your imagination slightly
ahead of this
beyond vacuum
why is no one exploring the seas in the
ocean i think lots of people are
exploring seas in the ocean much of
these exploration is classified perhaps
you have submarines you have deep
deep
deep sea submersibles
the alvin submersibles and so on
there is plenty of exploration happening
but maybe it is not something that
that
attracts a lot of media attention and
maybe it's stuff that is not really
spoken about because there may be
interesting things that you we may be
discovering which have commercial
applications maybe military applications
but exploration is happening but not to
the extent that one would want we still
don't know what's below the surface of
the ocean the oceans are deep
and very mysterious we know next to
nothing about it there could be unknown
species hiding out there maybe dinosaurs
hiding out there who knows
you know
maybe the great kraken is there
maybe the colossal mega colossal squid
is there maybe there could be a whole
who knows what's out there you know
so yeah
it's very hard it's very hard to do
undersea exploration
we know more about
the surface of the planet than what's
under the ocean
we know more about the solar system
you know then what may be under the
ocean in on our own planet so yeah there
is certainly a
significant paucity of knowledge and
understanding
of our undersea environment but there is
some explosion that's happening but it's
hard it's really hard
it's tough
okay let's see something else
can you explain the relations between
quantum theory and vedanta i don't know
any
see i am i am
not an expert in vedanta by any stretch
of the imagination
and when it comes to vedanta vedanta is
the
the end result of the vedas the vedas
are not scientific texts please
understand this i know this will offend
people some people think all the
information and knowledge in the world
is present in the vedas the vedas were a
cultural and religious
corpus
of writing
that's what the vedas were
the vedas were not scientific texts
there is no science
in the vedas
the vedas speak about indian society
from god knows how many thousands of
years ago and
beyond that i have not really studied
vedanta in great depth so
so
from
so from my limited limited perspective
of very small knowledge
i can say i know nothing about this
and i don't see any relationship between
quantum theory in vedanta or the vedas
now many people who have studied the
vedanta vedanta
they say there is quantum this and
quantum that
the only person who can authoritatively
speak about this is someone who has
studied quantum theory in great detail
and also studied the vedas and vedanta
in great detail i know no such person
so people who make these claims
i are either people who have studied
only one one of these two things
or people who studied nothing
so please don't take this very seriously
and please don't get offended at my
frank and candid remarks
i have the greatest amount of respect as
you would know i hope for indian culture
so it's not it's not about that
right okay
um
let's take one or two questions
more
how to become an astronaut in india
please tell us the process and will
there be enough crude missions in india
in the future
you want to be an astronaut in india
you need to be an air force fighter
pilot ideally a test pilot
that's the process
you have to go into the air force
you have to apply to be a fighter pilot
you have to go through the process the
selection process which is very tough
maybe one person would be admitted would
be accepted perhaps
you have to become a fighter pilot you
have to prove yourself to be a top class
fighter pilot
and then
you may be eligible
for possibly being an astronaut
so right now i believe there's a bunch
of uh
fighter pilots who are being clear
trained
to be the first astronauts who go on the
gaganyan mission which will happen
hopefully sometime soon
so that is the process initially there
will be very few crude missions
in this coming decade
eventually in the next 20 years 30 years
maybe you could we could have us
a space station of our own maybe a
moon base
maybe a mars base so in the next 20 30
years i am hopeful that there will be
sufficient crude missions
and then they would want to take people
who are not
necessarily fighter pilots
but as of today
you have to be a fighter pilot and a
top-class fighter pilot
to be a candidate for being an astronaut
in india
that's how i see things that's how
that's what i understand of this
okay let's take um one more question
let's see if there is um
will there be functional nuclear powered
rockets in the next 10 years
we have
at least one
nuclear-powered missile that we know of
it uses
a small nuclear reactor that creates
a ramjet effect so it's a
nuclear-powered ram jet so that's a
missile that will that can
fly within the earth's atmosphere now
what you're talking about is
nuclear-powered rockets that would
probably be for space launches and all
that
no it's not going to happen in the next
10 years it's certainly feasible it's
feasible for sure and there used to be
the the americans had uh had a program
that explored the possibility
of of going to mars by a bomb by nuclear
bomb
so that would be a massive rocket with a
very large mass
and it would be impelled propelled by
nuclear reactor nuclear explosions
atomic bombs
and they kind of showed that it would it
could work
but obviously there will be nuclear
fallout in the atmosphere and that's
something you don't want right you don't
want any more atmospheric nuclear
explosions
so uh most likely that will not happen
in the near future in the next 10 years
but maybe the the technology certainly
can work
it's certainly a viable
technology it's feasible
okay
one more question if let's see if
there's something interesting
ask me questions about science people
people asking
today is the day of science
why can't we dump all the plastic waste
into space towards the direction of the
sun some people say why don't you dump
all the nuclear waste into space solves
the problem
the thing is this
rockets can fail
rockets can explode you put nuclear
waste on a rocket
the rocket goes up and explodes then
what happens all that nuclear waste will
be all over the atmosphere it will fo it
will rain down all across the planet
or across
across a wide geography
similarly
i mean
how much plastic waste first of all can
you put on a rocket
a large rocket let's say the gslv
the gslv can carry how much
it's not a large amount of weight it can
carry
and
the amount of money it takes
to place one kilo of payload into orbit
is in the millions of dollars
so let's say you want to place a
thousand tons of plastic
into outer space a thousand tons
is
is a million
is a million kilos
a million kilos multiplied by a million
dollars million million
six that's 12 zeros that's how many
dollars you would need
to pay for that kind of space launch
which is prohibitively expensive
incredibly expensive
so that's why it's not feasible because
who will pay for that
right
it's not possible to pay for that much
that much money for for dumping plastic
into the into this into space
so there are these considerations
financial considerations other
considerations which make it impractical
to do such a thing that's the reason why
all right my dear friends we are at the
end of today's session thank you very
much for all the questions
was great for answering them
and i will see you in the next question
in in the next session science session
next week
and the other session will be tomorrow
so hope to see you there
until then take care
and good bye